<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Reverend Doctor Ambrose Atfield, late minister of St. Leonard Shoreditch, preached in the said parish church, March 19, 1683/4 by Richard Pearson ...</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12755800</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12755800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Reverend Doctor Ambrose Atfield, late minister of St. Leonard Shoreditch, preached in the said parish church, March 19, 1683/4 by Richard Pearson ...</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Holt, for D. Newman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Atfield, Ambrose, d. 1684.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 2nd, IV, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93424:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93424:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF THE Reverend Doctor <hi>AMBROSE ATFIELD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Late Miniſter of St. <hi>Leonard Shoreditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PREACHED In the ſaid Pariſh Church, <hi>March</hi> 19. 1683/4.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD PEARSON,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Crooked-Lane, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Holt,</hi> for <hi>D. Newman,</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:93424:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is deſired to take Notice, that the Publication hereof was chiefly occaſioned, and, in ſome ſort, made neceſſary, through <hi>the Lawleſs Inſolence</hi> of One, who, by the help of a <hi>Short-hand man</hi> (though confeſsing himſelf not able to write the ſame) ſome Weeks ago made bold to print the pretended Subſtance of this Sermon. By which unfair Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſame Perſon, in the like kind, as the Doctor had ſuffered not a little, while living; ſo this Zealous Penny-catcher knew no other way of making him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends now, but thus to wrong his Memory alſo, and the Credit of the Perſon who endeavoured to do right to it, by ſetting forth that ridiculous and most non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſical Pamphlet, calling it ſelf, and bawled about for <hi>Dr. Atfield's Funeral Sermon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93424:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 THES. 4. 13.</bibl>
               <q>But I would not have you be ignorant, Brethren, concerning them that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, that you ſorrow not even as others, that have no Hope.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall at preſent, without enquiring into the more particular dependence or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Words, conſider them only as a general Caution or Direction for Chriſtians, how to moderate their Paſſions, upon the death of Friends and Relations; what to avoid, and how to behave themſelves upon theſe occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And in the handling of the Words, I ſhall obſerve and endeavour to ſhew (ſo far as the Time will permit) theſe following Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That all ſorrow, upon the death of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93424:3"/> Friends, is not unallowable in, or forbidden Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That there is yet a great deal of difference in ſuch caſes, betwixt the ſorrow of a true Chriſtian, and that of others; and in what this difference chiefly conſiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Belief of a future State, or hopes of a joyful Reſurrection, which the one is endued with, and the other void of, is the main cauſe of this Difference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That in order to the exerciſe of ſuch a lively Hope, as may enable men to moderate their Grief, it is very neceſſary that Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould, according to the Apoſtles Example here, endeavour to correct in men all miſtakes, concerning the State of the <hi>Dead,</hi> and take care that they be well acquainted with, and often reminded of the <hi>right grounds</hi> of ſuch Hope. <hi>But I would not have you be ignorant, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, concerning them that are aſleep, that you ſorrow not even as others, that have no Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am to ſhew, (as ſuppoſed in my Text) That all ſorrow, upon the death of Friends, is not forbidden Chriſtians. If we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93424:3"/> look into the Practice and Examples of the beſt Saints of God under the Old Teſtament, we ſhall find them far enough from being ſtrangers to this affection of Grief, upon ſuch Occaſions. But on the contrary, we read both of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s weeping and mourning for <hi>Sarah, Gen.</hi> 23. 2. and of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s doing the like for <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 50. and of King <hi>David</hi>'s Lamentation over <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 17. and of the Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi>'s for King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 35. 25. Nay, it was cuſtomary, among the Jews, to allow no leſs than ſeven days of mourning to private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for their Relations; and for Princes and great Prophets, the whole People uſed to mourn thirty days; as appears upon the departure of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and others. Nor do we any where in the Word of God, find the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition or reprehenſion of this Practice; but on the contrary, though we do indeed meet with ſeveral places, wherein the Jews are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to follow the Example of the Heathen, and carefully to avoid their Extravagancies and Superſtitions, both as to the meaſure and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their mourning and expreſſions of Grief; yet ſo far is the Scripture from countenancing or encouraging any ſuch thing, as a Stoical Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy or Stupidity; in theſe caſes; that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93424:4"/> ſeems to complain of the ſame, as no ſmall fault, and to reprove people for not being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently affected, upon ſuch occaſions, Iſ. 57. 1. <hi>The Righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart,</hi> But ſtill, leſt any one ſhould object, that though under the Jewiſh Eiconomy men were indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in ſome infirmities, and ſeveral things then permitted, which under the Goſpel (that muſt be acknowledged to introduce and oblige to a greater Perfection) are not now allowable, and that all grief for the dead is to be looked upon and excluded under this Notion: Leſt any ſuch thing, I ſay, ſhould be ſuſpected; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that beſides there being no place in the New Teſtament, that can give any tolerable countenance to ſuch an Opinion, in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, there is enough, methinks, to make us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude quite otherwiſe, from the conſideration of what is expresſly recorded in Holy Writ, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saviour himſelf, whoſe Example in this (as in all other like caſes) may abundantly determine and ſatisfie us, concerning the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and lawfulneſs of things for us. But now we read of our Saviour himſelf, in the caſe of his Friend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that though he reſolved to raiſe him from the Dead, and at other times when he meant to do the like, he thought fit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93424:4"/> to ſuppreſs the Extravagancies of the Mourners tears (as <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 52. and <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 13.) yet now he does ſo much aſſert and countenance the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and juſtice of their ſorrow, as to he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Companion to them in the ſame, and it is accordingly expresſly recorded of him, <hi>John</hi> 11. 35. <hi>That Jeſus wept.</hi> Nor is it ſufficient to conceit (as ſome have done) that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's weeping here, was not at all, in reſpect of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or that he might firſt ſhew himſelf true man by his compaſſion, and partaking of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent infirmities, as he was preſently to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate himſelf the Son of God, by his raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him from the Dead; nor that he might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie us of the lawfulneſs of moderate Grief, upon ſuch occaſions; but that, on the contrary, his tears proceeded, meerly from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Infidelity of the ſtanders by, and out of a fore-ſight of the little ſucceſs this great Miracle would have upon them; or elſe that they were tears not of Grief, but Joy for the Glory that would redound to his Father, upon this occaſion: For ſuppoſe this aſſertion to be true (which is indeed highly improbable) yet had all grief for the death of Friends been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for Chriſtians, we may conclude that our Saviour would have taken care ſo to avoid all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93424:5"/> appearance of evil in himſelf, as to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſly told them that he did not weep upon the account of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> eſpecially ſince we cannot but grant him to know, how they both would and did interpret his tears, that ſtood by him; for (as it immediately follows in the 36 verſe) <hi>Then ſaid the Jews, behold how he loved him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill, if this Argument ſhould not yet be thought convincing; what ſhall we think of another place, where all ſorrow for the Dead, is ſo far from being reprehended, that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſly commended, by the Spirit of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the character of Devout men, Acts 8. 2. <hi>Who carried</hi> Stephen <hi>to his Burial, and made great Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation over him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this we may further add, that what is purely natural, cannot, without ſome reflection upon the God of Nature, be thought unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: But to expreſs ſome ſorrow at the death of Friends, ſeems to be ſo natural, that generally all People of the World, have ever agreed, both in the practice and decency of the thing, though moſt indeed have erred in the exceſs of this Paſſion, and unreaſonable manners of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it. And as for that Nation, which was of old, the only one remarkable for expreſſing no kind of ſorrow, upon this account, they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93424:5"/> were alſo no leſs remarkable for their giving no good reaſon, of their ſo different Practice. The Stoick Philoſophers alſo loved to vapour and amuze others with their impracticable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, whilſt all the Perfection they could ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at themſelves in that kind, was only to play the Hypocrites, by a little concealing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than truly conquering their Paſſions, and by ſeeming to triumph over Nature. Whereas that of <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> the Emperor, was a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſaying, and ſuch as ſhewed him to have well conſidered human Nature, who when young <hi>Antoninus,</hi> afterwards his Succeſſor, was diſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by the Courtiers, from lamenting the death of the Perſon that had brought him up, <hi>Suffer him</hi> (ſays the Emperour) <hi>to be a man; for neither Philoſophy, nor a Crown ought to root out our Affections.</hi> In ſhort, the Chriſtian Religion it ſelf does not deſtory, but only poliſh Nature; does not require that we ſhould wholly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, but only rightly govern our Paſſions and Affections, and keep them within the compaſs of Sobriety and Moderation, ſo that indeed it ſeems impoſſible that a man ſhould continue wholly unaffected with the death of a near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, unleſs he have firſt in him, more than a tincture of that Vice, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93424:6"/> name of <hi>a being void of natural Affection,</hi> Rom. 1. 31.</p>
            <p>And as moderate Grief, upon ſuch occaſions, ſeems to be natural, ſo is the ſame alſo not a little uſeful towards the Purpoſes of Religion; as diſpoſing Men towards a more ſerious and thorow Conſideration of the Vanity of the World, the Frailty of Humane Nature and their own Mortality. A moderately Warm Grief for a newly deceaſed Friend, helps Men to a more full Conviction of the Neceſſity and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, of neglecting to do no kind Offices to our Relations, whileſt they continue with us, but of endeavouring all we can, both by our own good Examples and Inſtructions, to farther them in the ways of Piety; ſince when they are gone, of all the good turns we have done them, this is the only Subſtantial Benefit that will ſtill remain with them, and we ſee that we are afterwards no more able to profit them by all we can further do, than if they had never been. Such Sorrow puts Men upon a more lively ſenſe of the great folly of doating upon any worldly thing, which we are ſure ſo ſhortly to leave for ever; how mad it is to lay up treaſure for our ſelves here, without endeavouring to be rich towards God. In ſhort, 'tis very Conducive towards Mens entertaining ſuch ſober, true thoughts of things,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93424:6"/> as may make them ſet looſe to the World, and become more ready to part with their Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, towards the relief of thoſe that need; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that while they continue thus affected, they ſeem to be quite other kind of Men than they were before.</p>
            <p>Thus even the covetous Aegyptians while their grief was kept freſh, by the dead Carkaſes of their Sons and Daughters and other Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that lay before them, they ſo little valued their choiceſt Treaſure, that they readily parted with it, and lent all their richeſt Jewels to the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> And indeed what kind of Men might we be, would we but endeavour to cheriſh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the like thoughts, which our Grief, upon ſuch Occaſions, does, for a time, almoſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will or no, put us upon? So great is the benefit of ſuch kindly Sorrow, that the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> makes no Scruple to affirm, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 3, 4. That <hi>the heart of the wiſe is in the Houſe of Mourning, and that by the ſadneſs of the Countenance, the heart is made better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, ſo far is ſome ſober previous Grief, upon ſuch juſt Occaſions, from being offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to God, or Inconſiſtent with that Conformity of our Wills to his, which is attainable and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us in this imperfect State, that indeed ſelf-Reſignation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93424:7"/> does rather, from hence, take its riſe and opportunity. For all Reſignation ſeems to ſuppoſe ſome former Reluctancy, or a foregoing Velleity, at leaſt, of having the thing otherwiſe; for I cannot be ſaid properly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign my ſelf, when I am only contented with that thing which I never had naturally any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to, nor could have wiſhed that it might have fallen out otherwiſe; there is no Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in offering up unto God of ſuch Things only as coſt us nothing. For it is no great matter to be ready to kiſs that Rod, of which we never yet felt the ſmart, or to be contented with that Loſs or Afflication, of which we were never ſenſible, or at all Affected with; this is rather Stupidity than Reſignation. Whereas this ſeems to be the Progreſs of genuine Reſignation. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that, by giving me this occaſion, upon which it is natural for Fleſh and Blood to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, God ſees it beſt that I ſhould be now ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful; I will therefore meekly own his Hand and Anſwer his call, and think it beſt for me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be ſo affected: but I will take care to grieve ſo as becomes a Man and a Chriſtian not beyond the due meaſure, nor with the leaſt repining; but fully approving in my Judgment, that choice which God has made for me, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93424:7"/> unpleaſing it may be to my Senſitive Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite and inferiour Faculties. Thus you ſee, a Man may be truly contented and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and yet ſufficiently ſenſible of an Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor does Reſignation exclude all, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuppoſe ſome Grief. And as in other Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſo for the loſs of Friends, a man may grieve lawfully. And therefore the Apoſtle here, does not ſay, That ye grieve not at all, but only, that ye grieve not immoderately, not as Heathen men uſed to do, <hi>not as others, who have no Hope.</hi> Which brings me now to the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second</hi> thing I was to ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is a great deal of difference in ſuch Caſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sorrow of a true Chriſtian, and that of others, and in what this Difference chiefly conſiſts. And now in order to this it will be firſt neceſſary for me to give you ſome brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how theſe others, that is, the Heathen, uſed to behave themſeves in ſuch Caſes. Whoſe Grief we ſhall find to exceed all bounds, to have beenboth highly extravagant &amp; exceſſive, as to the meaſure of it, and for the manner of expreſſing it, both unnatural, fooliſh, cruel, and full of the higheſt Impiety and Irreligion. They were generally ſo far from endeavouring to moderate their Grief, by Reaſon, that they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93424:8"/> uſed all the Arts imaginable to highten and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, even to Oſtentation, and a Priding themſelves in the greateſt Exceſſes of the ſame. They uſed not only to rent their Garments, but alſo to pluck off their Hair and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Bald; to tear their Cheeks, and Breaſts, to beat their Heads and cut their Fleſh, in Token of the moſt deſperate Lamentation. As is partly intimated, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 1. Where the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are forbidden, to cut themſelves or to make Baldneſs between their Eyes, for the Dead, as the Heathen uſed to do. To which Cuſtoms alſo, both that of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 17. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 6. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 3. and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, have an Evident Relation. Nor were they contented only to be thus exceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mad themſelves, but that the Folly might be effectually carried on with greater Pomp and Solemnity, the Relations of the Dead uſed to hire others, who were always ready at hand, upon ſuch Occaſions, and made it a common Trade, to run howling up and down, and to mangle themſelves in the moſt deſperate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>And as they dealt thus unnaturally with themſelves, ſo their moſt unreaſonable Grief, put them upon the moſt monſtrous Cruelties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93424:8"/> others. For both the <hi>Greecians</hi> and from them, the <hi>Romans,</hi> uſed to cut the Throats of living Men, at the Sepulchres of their Dead Friends; ſeveral Captives being frequently kept, or bought for that purpoſe, to be ſo murdered at the Funerals not only of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but many times of private Perſons. But when this Cuſtom began to ſeem to ſavour of too much Cruelty, they afterwards thought fit a little to change the ſame, for what they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted leſs Barbarous; not performing this Butchery by their own Hands, but forcing their Captives, called by them Gladiators; to fight with, and kill one another, whilſt themſelves look't on; giving thoſe only their Lives as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, who hap'ned to be moſt expert or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in the Art of Murdering.</p>
            <p>Nor ſtill did the mad Grief of theſe Heathen Mourners ſuffer them to ſtop here, but ſo ſullen did it make them, and full of the higheſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Impatience, that, as if they were fallen out with Heaven it ſelf, and were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to revenge the loſs of their Dead Friends, upon their Idols and ſuppoſed Gods, 'twas uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with them, when they Mourned for ſome great Perſons, both to batter and throw Stones at their Temples, to offer no Sacrifice, but to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93424:9"/> overturn the Altars of the Gods, and to caſt their Houſhold-Gods out of Doors; all which Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies were generally practiſed (as <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> relates) upon the Death of <hi>Germanicus.</hi> Such impious Frenzies did they fall into, whilſt they freely indulged themſelves to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, in this moſt unreaſonable Paſſion.</p>
            <p>Nay (to ſpeak the truth) even their more common Grief upon ſuch Occaſions, was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally expreſt by and accompanied with ſuch Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Follies, that ſome few of the wiſer ſort among themſelves ſeem to have been aſhamed of the ſame; as <hi>Tully</hi> in particular, in his Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culan Queſtions, and <hi>Lucian</hi> in his Book <hi>de Luctu;</hi> who both more particularly acquaints us with their Cuſtom, and wittily repreſents the Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſs of it. Of which Paſſage, becauſe ſome even among us who ſhould ſhew themſelves Men and Chriſtians, are apt enough to fall into the like Extravagancies, I ſhall therefore think it worth the while here, briefly to acquaint you with the Subſtance. It is a Cuſtom (ſaith he) for the Father and Mother, coming forth from the reſt of the Kindred, to ſpread themſelves over the dead Body, and to accoſt it in a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and moſt Lamentable Voice, after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Alas my dear Son, thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93424:9"/> art dead, ſnatcht away before thy time, leaving me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; thou ſhalt no more Eat, nor Drink, nor wear Cloaths; thou ſhalt never Marry, go to War, or exerciſe any Trade, no more Walk, or be merry with thy Equals; no coming to be an Old Man.</hi> To which <hi>Lucian</hi> himſelf replys: <hi>Since you ſeem to be ſo Ignorant, I will teach you how to lament more truly; for why had you not as good ſay thus? Alas! dear Child, thou ſhalt no more Hunger, Thirſt, or be acold; poor Wretch! thou ſhalt never be affraid of War, or of the Tyrant; never more be weary, or feel the ſmart of Diſeaſes, never come to experience the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of Old Age;</hi> &amp;c. Would not ſuch a Lamentation now as this, be moſt Ridiculous? and yet all this is indeed implyed in the former.</p>
            <p>But thus much now may be <hi>ſufficient,</hi> as a taſte, to acquaint you, how theſe <hi>others</hi> uſed to ſorrow, and what great Extravagancies the Heathen were guilty of therein. To all which, they who profeſs themſelves Chriſtians ought to be ſo far ſtrangers, that (in the judgment of both <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> and St. <hi>Cyprian)</hi> they who can afford to indulge themſelves in the like Exceſſes, are guilty of offering the higheſt ſcandal to others, do affront their own Principles, and diſgrace their Profeſſion, and may be juſtly ſuſpected not indeed to believe what they pretend, but, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93424:10"/> and in effect, to have as bad as renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Chriſtian Faith. For the ſincere Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's Grief, in ſuch caſes, is ſober, moderate, natural, and ſilent, endeavouring to keep it ſelf ſecret, and far from all manner of Oſtentation; far from putting Men upon the Exerciſe of any ſuch unnatural Cruelties, either upon themſelves or others, but rather inclining them to be more open, tender-hearted and extenſive in Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, and Acts of Beneficence, towards all thoſe who need their Charity. Much leſs will a true Diſciple of Chriſt ever ſuffer his Sorrow ſo far to extinguiſh the Force of his Reaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as that he ſhould ſullenly murmur or repine at God's dealings with him, or fooliſhly charge Providence: But on the contrary, though he be duly ſenſible of the Affliction, and can thereupon experience in himſelf ſomething of the common Weakneſſes of Humane Nature; yet he never allows his Paſſion to riſe to ſuch a hight, but that in <hi>his</hi> Mind and Judgment <hi>he can</hi> both approve of and reſt heartily ſatisfyed with what Providence ſees beſt ſhould befall him; and in the midſt of all his Sorrow, can, ever and anon, with a comfortable mixture of the Tears of Joy, ſay; <hi>Good, and Wiſe, and Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is this Diſpenſation of the Lord; Thy Will, O
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93424:10"/> Father, not mine be done; or</hi> with holy Job, in the ſame caſe, <hi>The Lord gave and the Lord hath taken away, Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> Thus you ſee how wide a difference there is betwixt theſe two; even as much as betwixt the Grief of thoſe who have yet a Subſtantial Support &amp; Comfort at Hand, and that of thoſe who ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpair, and have therefore loſt all Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Which brings me now to the third and laſt Propoſicion that the Time will give me leave to proſecute, and that too briefly, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Belief of a future State, or the Hope of a joyful Reſurrection which the one is endued with, and the other void of, is indeed the main cauſe of this great Difference. 'Tis no great wonder that the poor Heathen ſhould be ſo carried on by the Tide of their Extravagant Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſo billedged with the Flood<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Tears, and even ſunk by the <hi>moſt deſperate</hi> Grief; ſince they wanted both the Compaſs of God's Word to ſtear themſelves by, and the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that ſure Anchor of Hope, with both which we Chriſtians are ſo abundantly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht. For bare natural Reaſon, eſpecially whileſt it was ſo clog'd and prejudiced, by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93424:11"/> the force of prevailing Cuſtom, was too weak ſufficiently to correct the Extravagancies of their Paſſions, and keep them within their due Bounds. For with what Anguiſh and extreme Diſpair muſt they needs be poſſes't, while they beheld thoſe dear Relations ſnatch't from them, who, whilſt living, were the very joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their hearts, and had no ſufficient Grounds to hinder them from more than ſuſpecting, that they ſhould never have an opportunity of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying them any more forever, but that they were loſt and utterly extinguiſhed to all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? what unſupportable Grief muſt needs be conſequent under the diſadvantage of ſuch black and melancholick Apprehenſions?</p>
            <p>But we Chriſtians are thorowly aſſured, that there is moſt certainly a State beyond the Grave; and that, as to the Righteous, <hi>there is Hope in his Death,</hi> Prov. 14. 32. We are naturally apt to lament the Death of the beſt <hi>Men</hi> moſt; but now to prevent all Exceſſes in this caſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, the Goſpel has furniſhed us with the moſt effectual Remedy; unleſs we can find in our hearts either to lament or envy their being removed to a State of ſo infinitely greater Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and Perfection. We are aſſured that they are not periſh't, but only gone before;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93424:11"/> that their Spirits are preſently received into the hands of God their moſt faithful Creatour; and that thoſe Carcaſſes alſo which we now ſee laid in the Grave, and ſown in Corruption, ſhall in due time be raiſed Spiritual Bodies and in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, every way fitted for ſuch a Re-union with the Soul, as may render the happineſs of the whole man moſt perfect and complete.</p>
            <p>In the mean time therefore though Nature and Decency do ſeem to allow ſome moderate tears, upon theſe occaſions, yet how can we find in our hearts, even now, to be exceſſive? ſince we who ſurvive may conſider, that after a few more days dream't over, ſeparate Friends ſhall meet again, to part no more forever; and that too, (if we do but now take care duly to prepare our ſelves for the ſame) in ſuch a bleſſed State, as that we ſhall hereafter wonder at our former frailty and weakneſs, that we ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo loath to part from each other here, in order to it; and ſo apt to deplore the loſs, the Priviledge of thoſe who went but a little before us.</p>
            <p>That there is indeed a future State, and that the Dead ſhall be raiſed to live forever, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, we know, as ſure as that Chriſt himſelf is already riſen; for <hi>becauſe he lives, we ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93424:12"/> live alſo;</hi> and that he indeed ſo lives, we have as much reaſon to be aſſured of, as 'tis poſſible for us to have in the very nature of the thing, and at this Diſtance. Let us not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhame and contradict the Faith we profeſs, by any unagreeable Practices: But whileſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who know no better, indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in immoderate Grief, and Prophane and Effeminate Lamentations, ſeaſonably dry up our Tears; and, behaving ourſelves as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thoſe who profeſs themſelves Children of the Reſurrection, breaking other into thoſe Triumphant W<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of St. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (which our Church alſo fitly Remind<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55 <hi>O Dea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, where is thy Sting, O Grave, where is thy Victory? Thanks be to God, who giveth us the Victory, through our Lord Jeſus Christ,</hi> or in that of 1 Pet. 1. 3. <hi>Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant Mercy, hath begotten us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unto a lively Hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead.</hi> To conclude, Brethren, we ſhall ſhew our ſelves to be far worſe than <hi>ignorant, as concerning</hi> them that are aſleep, if, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Occaſions; we do not take care ſo to moderate our Grief, as becomes Chriſtians, but give our ſelves leave <hi>to ſorrow, even as others, that have no Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93424:12"/>
            <p> And now, having done with my Text, I ſhall only ſay ſomething, with a more Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Regard to that ſad and Afficting Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which has, at preſent, brought us here together, to perform that laſt Office for our dear and Reverend Friend.</p>
            <p>By whoſe Deceaſe, indeed, I muſt needs ſay, we are preſented with no ordinary Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the exerciſe of a truly Chriſtian Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; and that too perhaps, even to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Degrees of Grief, which may be well conſiſtent with ſuch exceeding good Hope, as (God be praiſed) we have every way ſo juſt reaſon to entertain.</p>
            <p>He was a <hi>Perſon</hi> generally well known, and had the <hi>Happineſs</hi> as well as <hi>Merit</hi> to be as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally well beloved and reſpected; and the loſs of him now will, I'm confident, be no leſs univerſally Lamented.</p>
            <p>For indeed, how can it be expected, that he, who was ſo dear and ſingularly uſeful, in all his ſeveral Relations and Capacities, both Private and Publick; that he, who was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and agreeable a Husband, ſo ſweet and tender a Father, ſo Affectionate and Benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al a Kinſman, ſo ſincere and faithful a Friend, ſo conſtant a Reliever of and ſo many ways a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93424:13"/> Benefactor to the Poor; and in a Word, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently Pleaſant, ſo admirably Courteous and Obliging in his Converſation, and (to his Power) ſo really Beneficial unto all; how can ſuch a Perſon, who was all this, and much more, be now ſnatch'd away from us, and not leave many a heavy Heart and weeping Eye behind him?</p>
            <p>And what Reaſon have you of this Pariſh to deplore the loſs of ſo Diligent, Pious, and Faithful a Miniſter? And may I not alſo ſay, the whole City in General, in that they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the Benefit of ſo conſtant and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, ſo ready and very uſeful a Preacher?</p>
            <p>Could he at all, need it, or had I any Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent at giving Characters, I might certainly have a ſafe and fruitful Opportunity to exerciſe the ſame, at preſent: But yet, as it would be more eaſie, ſo 'tis withal leſs neceſſary, to be large in the Commendations of ſuch a Perſon, whom every Body elſe alſo has been ſo ready to value and commend, that, perhaps, ſcarce any other Honeſt Regular Clergy-man of his Time in <hi>England,</hi> ever came nearer, than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has done, towards the making a happy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to that General Woe denounced againſt thoſe, <hi>of whom all Men ſhall ſpeak well.</hi> For now
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93424:13"/> and then a moſt rare Example is to be found, of a Perſon that ſhall Faithfully and Impartially continue to diſcharge his Duty towards all, and yet not happen to make any, thereby, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Enemies: But have the peculiar Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo to charm or ſilence even the worſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Perſons, as that Malice it ſelf ſhall not once dare to open it's Mouth againſt him; but, out of meer ſhame, or diſpair of gaining Credit, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying that, which it cannot be ſo blind as not to be ſenſible, would ſerve to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but only to procure to it ſelf the General Hatred and Diſgrace of others.</p>
            <p>And ſo, as to our deceaſed Brother, thus much I dare affirm, that very few, if any, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have, or will ſay any other than well of him.</p>
            <p>The only Inſtance of any thing like an ill Reflection that I could ever hear ſo much as Attempted to be caſt upon him (and which, to do right to his Memory, I think it not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, at this time, to take notice of) was ſuch a thing, as, when thorowly underſtood, will, I make no queſtion, tend rather every way to his deſerved Commendation.</p>
            <p>Now ſome have been ready to Object it, as an Argument of ſomething of a greedy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93424:14"/> that he ſhould hold ſeveral Lectures, in the City, and more eſpecially his Sunday-night Lecture.</p>
            <p>But God forbid that his Triple-pains and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in Preaching ſhould, in it ſelf, be look't upon, by any, as a fault in him. And that he was far from doing this, out of any ſuch Sordid Motive, there needs no other Argument or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, than this, That he did not put up any thing of the Money, but conſtantly gave away the whole Forty Pound <hi>per Annum</hi> towards the uſes of a <hi>generous Charity.</hi> And he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as readily deſiſted from that Employment, as ſoon as he underſtood, that Authority thought it not ſo convenient, in ſome reſpects, that it ſhould be, at that Time and Place, any longer continued.</p>
            <p>But I need not have ſaid any thing of this, had it not been for the ſake of ſome, who may happen to have been leſs acquainted with him.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe of this Pariſh, they know full well, and, I hope, will always gratefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, how ready he was both to give, and forgive, ſo much commonly every Year, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no inconſiderable Sum. To ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of how Chearfully he, at all times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed his Charitable Pains among the Poorer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93424:14"/> ſort, not only freely forgiving them his Dues, but frequently alſo, as he ſaw Occaſion, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more out of his own Pocket, inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from them. I ſpare to add much more of what was highly Commendable in him, and might evidence him to have been a Perſon tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faithful in his ſeveral Relations, and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Serviceable in his Generation; ſince the Conſideration of theſe things does, in it ſelf, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tend only to Aggravate our Sorrow for the loſs of him. Which yet that it may not, in any one, exceed the due Bounds of a Chriſtian Moderation in theſe Caſes, we are therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to conſider, that the ſame things which make us ſo ſenſible of our own loſs, are turned to his unſpeakable Gain and endleſs Happineſs; who having behaved himſelf like a good and faithful Servant, is now entered into the Joy of his Lord; and having been ſo Inſtrumental, by his godly Example as well as Doctrine, to turn (as we have good reaſon to hope) many, unto Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is now called from us, to take a Place among thoſe other Stars of Glory.</p>
            <p>Thus, unleſs we be willing too much to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge our ſelves in a fond kind of ſelf-love, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to ſhew a diſcreet Love towards him, ſuch good Hope as this, muſt needs be of it ſelf
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93424:15"/> ſufficient, to mix ſuch Subſtantial Comfort with our Sorrow, as will be ſure to keep it within the juſt Limits of a truly Chriſtian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</p>
            <p>In order to which end of moderating our Grief, though it may ſeem Impertinent, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this main Foundation of Comfort, to add any thing elſe, to the ſame purpoſe; yet one Conſideration more, I cannot well tell how to forbear; ſince it ſo naturally offers it ſelf from the peculiar Temper, and moſt Remarkable Example of the Perſon himſelf deceaſed; in which, indeed, he has left us all, who were well acquainted with him (if we do but take care, not to deprive our ſelves of it, by want of endeavour to imitate) a very rare and moſt valuable Legacy.</p>
            <p>For he was a Man whoſe Mind was always ſo Calm and even, of a Temper ſo Serene and well Compoſed, his Heart ſo Chriſtianly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to Providence, and ſo admirably fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt all the uſual Croſs Occurrences of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life, that, as I much queſtion whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one can ſay, that ever he obſerved him Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with the Paſſion of Anger, ſo I ſcarcely believe that ever he was ſeen oppreſſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of exceſſive Grief, upon any Occaſion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93424:15"/>
            <p> He had learnt to bear the Death of other Friends, with ſuch wonderful Patience, and would ſo Familiarly and Reconciledly talk of his own, that I am bound to be a grateful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledger, of how excellent Influence his very Converſation was, towards the Satisfaction and Compoſing the Minds of others, in the like Caſes.</p>
            <p>Nor was his Temper or Beheaviour, in the leaſt, altered, when he came to be Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Exerciſed, by his laſt and moſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sickneſs: But tho he had before enjoy'd conſtant good Health for a great while toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which uſually makes Men leſs able to bear the Tryal of ſuch Pains; yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remember that ever I beheld any Inſtance of a more Exemplary Patience. Perfectly reſigned he was, either for Life or Death, as God ſhould ſee fit to diſpoſe of him; and when at laſt he perceived his Time drawing near, took his laſt Farewell of his Relations, with moſt Pious Exhortations to them, and uſeful Counſels; and then, meekly reſigned up his Spirit, into the Hands of him that gave it.</p>
            <p>Thus Calmly he lived, and thus he dy'd,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93424:16"/> an Eminent Pattern of a meek and quiet Mind, of admirable Tranquillity and Reſignation. So that I am half perſuaded, that even his Cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Air, and compoſed Countenance, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impreſſed on our Memories, and the due conſideration how he uſed conſtantly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean himſelf in the like Caſes, may prove no inſucceſsful Antydote againſt, or be enough to ſhame one out of any Extravagant Paſſion, of what ſort ſoever.</p>
            <p>And methinks, at leaſt, (if Grief will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Teaching) the moſt Calm and Manly ſort of Sorrow, ſhould beſt befit the Funerals of Dr. <hi>Atfield.</hi> Nor will it become us now, (if we rightly value his Memory or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) to ſorrow as others, who have no Hope; nor yet to ſorrow for him, as for others, even where there is the ſame good Hope.</p>
            <p>And now, to conclude all; There is but one thing more remaining, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Chriſtian Office we are going to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form) we are ſtill capable of doing for him; for our ſelves I ſhould ſay; and yet, why may I not ſay, for both?</p>
            <p>Since it is reaſonably ſuppoſeable, that his Joy, even in the other State; may be more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93424:16"/> encreaſed to all Eternity, by our ſeaſonable Practice, of what I am going to direct you to. Which is no other, in ſhort, than this, that we would all take ſpecial care, to let his Godly Example, and wholeſom Doctrines, all his pious Counſels and good Advice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Private, or Publick, have Reſpectively their due Influence, and Effect upon our Minds, and Lives.</p>
            <p>This, this is the way, the only way to make him ſtill live among us, tho he be gone from us; by this means, tho he be Dead, he will yet ſpeak not only to, but in us. And ſo when we our ſelves come alſo (as he has already done) to put off theſe Earthly Tabernacles we may Joyfully meet him again, to part no more for ever; and not only him, but alſo all other of our Friends, departed hence in the true Faith, and fear of God; when we ſhall be truly <hi>come unto Mount Sion, to the City of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, and to an Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Company of Angels, to the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and Church of the firſt-born; and to God the Judg of all, and to the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Mediator of the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and there be for ever preſent with the Lord, in that bliſsful State;</hi> where <hi>God ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93424:17"/> wipe away all Tears from our Eyes, and there ſhall be no more Death, neither Sorrow nor crying; neither ſhall there be any more Pain; but all theſe former things being paſſed away,</hi> there ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a new Scene, of Joys unſpeakable, and Life and Happineſs Everlaſting. To which, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93424:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
